Levine. Louis. Women's Garment Workers, Manuscript. 6036/005
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Levine. Louis. Women's Garment Workers Manuscript.
1924-1924
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Levine, Louis
6036/005
2.5 cubic feet
2.5 linear ft.
Articles, reprints, pamphlets, correspondence, photographs.
This collection includes drafts of Louis Levine's "The Women's Garment Workers" (1924), notes and collected materials about the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.
5767216
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, August 30, 2011
EAD encoding:
Kathryn Dowgiewicz, January 10, 2013
Biographical / Historical
Founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States, the ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. In 1995, the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) to form the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE).
Biographical / Historical
Louis Levine (Lewis Lorwin) was a noted economist and labor historian. He was born in the Ukraine on December 3, 1883. After coming to the United States as a young boy and studying both in the U. S. and abroad, he received a Ph. D. from Columbia University in 1912. Levine was an economic advisor for the New York State Labor Department from 1912 to 1916. He held numerous lecturer and professorship positions at colleges and universities across the country including Columbia, Wellesley College, University of Montana, and Beloit College. Levine was a staff member at the Brookings Institution from 1925 to 1935 and also taught and served as acting director at the Brookings Graduate School of Economics and Government. In 1934, Levine helped to found the National Planning Association, and beginning in 1935, he was an economic advisor to the International Labor Office in Geneva. During the 1940s, Levine served as an economic advisor to various agencies including the National Resources Planning Board, the Foreign Economic Administration, and the Office of International Trade in the Department of Commerce.
Levine authored many books on economics and international relations such as "The Labor Movement in France," "The Taxation of Mines in Montana," and "The Women's Garment Workers." In 1961, Levine was the recipient of the John Dewey Medal from the League for Industrial Democracy. He died in June 1970 at the age of 86.
Scope and Contents
Published in 1924, "The Women's Garment Workers" is a comprehensive history of the first twenty four years of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. The book also provides background information on the women's garment industry, its beginnings, early conditions, struggles, and the initial attempts at unionization which laid the foundation for the birth of the ILGWU. The collection encompasses author Louis Levine's research and notes for "The Women's Garment Workers," offering a glimpse into his writing process. Included are handwritten notes by Levine reviewing AFL convention proceedings to find references to the ILGWU, and notes and research on benefits, such as death, disability, sick and strike. There are clippings and collected articles on various topics along with Levine's notes on subjects ranging from Chicago cloak makers, the cloak and suit industry, and financial information. Levine took notes after reviewing the General Executive Board meeting minutes. Also available is material from various locals. Part of the collection is arranged by specific topics, including organizing, hours and wages, socialism, strike reports, as well as miscellaneous material at the end of the collection arranged by date. The other half of the collection is arranged by chapters for the book and contains notes, research, facts and dates. Of particular interest to the researcher is the large amount of research and primary sources that Levine has collected for the purpose of writing his book that provides historical information on the ILGWU.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records
Levine, Louis.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5767216
- American Federation of Labor (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Benefits (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Chapters 1-4 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Chapter 5 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Chapter 7 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Chapter 8 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Chapter 9 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Chapter 10 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Chapter 11 (10-13?) (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Chapter 12 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Chapter 13 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Chapter 14 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Chapter 15 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Chapter 16 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Chapter 19 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Chapter 20 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Chapter 21 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Chapter 22 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Chapter 23 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Chapter 24 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Chapter 25 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Chapter 26; Hourwich Affair, 1913-1914 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Chapter 27 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Chapter 28 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Chapter 31 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Chapter 34 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Chapter 35 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Chapter 36 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Chapter 37 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Cloak industry, Canada (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Cloakmakers, Chicago (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Cloak and suit industry, New York (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Cloak and suit industry, New York, 1912-1913 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Cloak industry, New York, 1918-1922 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Cloak industry joint board, New York, 1912-1916 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Cloak industry, Philadelphia (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Council of conciliatoin, 1915-1916 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Finances (Box 3, Folder 9)
- General Executive Board Minutes, 1914-1923 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Herman Grossman and strike call, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Hillquit, Blumberg, Uviller (jobber-contractor) (Box 4, Folder 2)
- History of the union (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Hours of labor (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Jurisdictional disputes (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Ladies' Garment Workers reviews, 1924-1932 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes letter from Fannia Cohn.
- Leaflets, union (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Leaflets, circulars and publications, union and non-union (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Locals, general (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Local 10 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Local 15 and 50, Philadelphia Waist and Dressmakers (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Local 20, Raincoat workers (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Local 33 and 34, Corset workers (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Local 66, Embroidery workers (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Local 90, Ladies tailors, dressmakers (Box 4, Folder 15)
- New York Times references, 1914-1916 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Newspaper clippings, 1915-1924 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Newspaper clippings, problems in needle trades, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Organizing out-of-town shops (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Problems and programs, 1923-1924 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- References, 16-20 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Resolutions-International office, General Executive Board, meetings and organizers (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Resolutions-Ideals and theories (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Resolutions-Policies and methods (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Socialism and Women's suffrage (Box 4, Folder 25)
- St. Louis, Louisville (Box 5, Folder 1)
- State reports (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Strike reports, 1909-1910 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  Chapter 21, part 3.
- Trachtenberg, Alexander, Director of ILGWU Department of Records and Research, 1920-1921 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  Correspondence.
- Waist and dress protocal, analysis of meetings, 1913-1916 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Miscellaneous material, general (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Miscellaneous material (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Miscellaneous material, 1918-1923 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Miscellaneous material, 1913-1914 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Miscellaneous material, 1910-1914 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Miscellaneous material, 1903-1907 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Miscellaneous material, 1900-1910 (Box 5, Folder 12)